Inventory of the Garrett Family Papers 1786-1928
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Letters, 1825-1928, n.d. (Box 1-2)
  - Letters, 1860-1869., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:7-8)
    - B[enjamin F. Garrett, Clover Station, [Virginia], to "brother" [Dr. Robert M. Garrett], n.p., 3 Dec[embe]r 1862., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Informs him that George and his family have been staying with him since last summer; assures him that George has quit drinking and will hopefully do well; has been enjoying the company of Laura and family, who is at Hampden Sydney College in Prince Edward County; has a good crop this year but find groceries and salt difficult to obtain; purchased salt for $25 a bushel last week, corn sells for $10 a barrel and wheat at $4 a bushel; describes the prosperity of the tobacco farmers in these times; feels that "times will be worse after 1st of January if Lincoln attempts to carry out his Emancipation Proclamation"; assures him that "our success [in winning the war] is certain"; informs him that Burnside will fight at Fredericksburg but is sure Gen. Lee will defeat him whenever they meet.
    - J.W. Blair, Richmond, [Virginia], to Dr. [Robert M.] Garrett, n.p., 3 Dec[embe]r [18]62., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Is now at the Military Institute [Virginia Military Institute] in Lexington; is told that a young man cannot be gotten in there, and that expenses are quite high, being $400-$500 per year; asks that Winder brings a letter to his [JWB] son Daniel in Col. Gorgas' department if he comes up; will write to Col. Smith and his son will write to him [RMG] as soon as possible.
    - Asa Hartz, Johnson's Island [Federal Prison], Lake Erie, to Miss A., n.p., [25 December] 1863., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Decided to write to her, though he does not know her, when Col. W. read parts of her letter to him; has let his imagination wander to think of his home in the South, and wishes "'this cruel war was over'"; has amused himself by coaxing a rat out of his hole and then throwing Col. W.'s toothbrush at him; joined the Confederate Army with the notion "that it was a mighty funny thing; that there was a good joke in it somewhere, & that I was the Columbus to discover it"; finally "found the joke -- [through] curiosity morbid curiosity" when he stumbled upon a group of Union troops who pressed him to go with them, and so became a prisoner; asks her not to mention that he wishes to go back again; describes an "exchange" ceremony (a funeral); closes with poetry that makes clear his desire to receive a letter from someone back in Dixie.
    - W. R[obertson] Garrett, Williamsburg, [Virginia], to "cousin" [?], n.p., 6 Feb[ruary] 1866., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Hopes that she will stop in Williamsburg on her way to Richmond to visit Cousin Mary Howard; shares news of many friends and relatives; informs her that Mary Garrett, daughter of Uncle Ben[jamin Garrett], is visiting and breaking many hearts; urges her to visit while Mary is there also.
    - W. R[obertson] Garrett, W[illia]msburg, Virginia, to "aunt" L[auretta] A. Savage, Eastville, Virginia, 9 Ap[ri]l 1866., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Apologizes for his lack of correspondence; refutes the statement she made in her previous letter "about an 'old aunt who gives offence [sic] by showing an interest in the family'"; assures her that she is well- loved by all but that the younger generation is "very negligent in the little etiquettes of life"; informs her that Comfort is visiting them, but will leave soon as she is afraid of the smallpox and fears it will reach Hickory Grounds; shares the news that Winder [Garrett] is in love with Miss Bettie Custis and Van with Miss Jenn Bright.
    - C[omfort?] [?]. Nottingham, Hickory Grounds, to "auntie" [?], n.p., 25 Dec[ember] 1866., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Has not been able to get up to Eastville to get the blankets, paper, or envelopes for her since it has either rained, snowed, or been very cold lately; cannot "see the slightest probability of borrowing you any money" and Mother cannot make her a comfort; informs her that Nancy has not been able to work since last August, Patience has been sick, and the new cook has been in bed almost every day since she arrived, so all the work of the house lands on Mother; looked in Eastville for blankets but found only common ones that would not suit her.
    - C[omfort] L.G. N[ottingham], Hickory Grounds, to "auntie" L[auretta] A. Savage, Williamsburg, Virginia, 10 Dec[ember] 1867., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Encloses the receipt of the deposit in First National Bank and asks that she let her know as soon as she receives it; informs her that Capt. Turner died a few days before; shares the news that Cousin R. took Mollie away with him and that Uncle John left a few minutes before for the island; asks when she will visit; would like Aunt Susan and Lottie to send her some scraps of worsted for her bed quilt; shares news of friends and relatives.
    - C[omfort] L.G. Nottingham, Hickory Grounds, to "auntie" [?], n.p., 4 June 1868., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Received a letter from Miss Sarah Mallett telling her of the extreme illness of Cousin Susan, being of the heart; was informed that Dr. Yardley thought Susan could not live through the night; informs her that Miss Lizzie Savage is visiting Eyre Hall; shares news of the activities of various relatives; describes the damage caused by windstorms; fears that they will have no fruit this year as the cold spring has destroyed the crop; have been two fires since last she wrote, and a neighbor's stable with all his horses and a cow were burned.
    - Capt. W. Robertson Garrett, Pulaski Giles County, Tennessee, to "aunt" [?], n.p., 3 Aug[ust] 1868., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Was elected a Professor at Giles College on the fourth of July; does not wish to take her money because she needs to have it for herself; informs her how to send a box or a trunk, but also tells her that it would be very costly, and believes the clothes will be suitable for the boys; informs her that John is back from Scotland and would like to teach school.
  - Letters, 1870-1889., 19 items. (Box-folder 1:9-10)
    - Mary [?], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to "aunt" [?], n.p., 16 November 1870., 3 pages. Incomplete. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Asks if she thinks she is an affectionate niece, "to write to my old Aunt twice a week"; informs her that Mrs. Taliaferro is back in Williamsburg after a trip to Canada; has organized a choir of the Mercer family, since the Southalls refused to participate; shares the news that Mary Stubbs has a baby girl about three weeks old, but does not know what she will name her; is pleased with the visits that Mr. Tucker and his wife make to her family.
    - Mary [?], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to "aunt" L[auretta] A. Savage, Eastville, Virginia, 8 Dec[ember] 1870., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Received the box of presents she sent; thanks her for the two beautiful dresses she sent; has made up her black Africa dress and feels very exquisite in it; informs her of the loss of Mary Stubbs' infant daughter; shares the news that Mr. Southall and Lizzie have a baby daughter; the election at the Asylum has retained all the old officers; expects Miss Fanny Crump for a visit the first of January; informs her that "one of your Eastern Shore girls," Miss Brown, has visited Williamsburg, and that she likes her a great deal.
    - [W. Robertson Garrett], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to "auntie" [?], n.p., 19 May 1871., 1 page. ALS. Incomplete. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Informs her that a decision has been made in her suit against W[illia]m Evans; explains that the suit took so long to settle because the court was trying to determine exactly how much money was due her; informs her that the amount due her should be paid within four months from the date of the decree.
    - W. R[obertson] Garrett, Pulaski, Tenn., to "auntie" [?], n.p., 6 Aug[ust] 1871., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Writes for information on Aunt Charlotte's condition, as he has been informed that she is very ill; explains that Van's engagement has been terminated as his fianc饬 Miss Mattie Children, has run off and married Mr. Lindsay of Pulaski; describes Van as bearing this information "very nobly and I think is not seriously wounded"; informs her that their new house will be complete the first of September and begs her to come see it.
    - Mary [?], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to "aunt" L[auretta] A. Savage, Eastville, Virginia, 8 Aug[ust] 1871., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Informs her that Ma has put off her visit to the Eastern Shore until Van comes to visit his home, since she will be able to stay longer if she waits; is relieved that Aunt Charlotte is much better now; explains that Miss Mary Sherwell is to go to New York for a few weeks because her health is bad; expects Professor Garrett and his bride later in the month.
    - C[omfort] L.G. N[ottingham], Balt[imore, Maryland], to "auntie" [?], n.p., 9 Jan[uary] 1873., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Has written Mr. Nottingham in regards to the bond he owes and will write to her as soon as he responds; expects to lose at least half the amount due from Mr. Shellan's estate; shares news of family and friends.
    - C[omfort] L.G. N[ottingham], Balt[imore, Maryland], to "auntie" [?], n.p., 8 July 1873., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Has been very ill for a long time; wanted to return to Northampton the next day, but as she is still too weak to dress, she will have to wait at least another week; mentions the death of Uncle Tom Nottingham after a long illness; informs her of the activities of other members of the family.
    - C[omfort] L.G. N[ottingham], Balt[imore, Maryland], to "auntie" [?], n.p., 22 July 1873., 4 pages. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Has been better lately; has been diagnosed by Dr. Page as being worn down from "nervous depression"; has been advised to travel a bit in order to recover fully; received an invitation to visit with a family in the Blue Ridge section of Maryland and will go there in a few days; expects to travel to Northampton later in the season; informs her that Miss Lucie Jamison (the sister of Cousin Carrie Nottingham) is quite ill and is expected to pass away soon; has been informed by Mr. and Mrs. Custis of Accomac that the railroad will run through Northampton, a desirable prospect if it increases property value. 4 pp. ALS.
      Includes AN from C[omfort] L.G. N[ottingham], Balt[imore, Maryland], to "auntie" [?], n.p., n.d., thanking her for her "kind thoughtfulness" and asking her to come to visit during the cold weather. 1 p.
    - Sue [?], Williamsburg, Virginia, to "auntie" [?], n.p., 1 Jan[uary] 1874., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Thanks her for the wonderful Christmas presents she sent; mentions that the whole family misses her a great deal; informs her that Mr. Wharton went to Norfolk for the holidays and has a new suit of clothes; cannot understand the extravagance of Mr. Wharton unless he is seriously debating matrimony; mentions that they have received a letter from Julia in which there was enclosed a photograph of Rob; was upset to hear of Uncle John's poor health and hopes Cousin Comfort is better.
    - Mary [?], Gloucester, [Virginia], to sister Sue [?], n.p., 17 June 1874., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Will be very accomplished when she returns home as Dr. Tabb has been teaching her how to eat fish, play whist, and boil eggs; asks for news of Winder; mentions that she is fast becoming a brunette and enjoying it; describes the pleasantness of being near the water; asks for news of friends and family and sends greetings to many.
    - Winder [Garrett], Cleburn, Johnson County, Texas, to "father" [Dr. Robert M. Garrett], n.p., 5 July 1874., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Has been asked by the editor of the Cleburn Chronicle to reply to an attack on Gov. Coke by the Galveston News, and to condense some articles from the New York Herald; has yet to take out his license to practice law; describes the town of Cleburn as being "a tolerable little country town, with a population of about 1200, and growing quite fast"; informs him that the prairie lands in this area will produce 20,000 bales of cotton, which will sell for $50-$75 per bale; gives the prices of flour ($6 a barrel), good cows ($6 a head), horses ($25-$50), and corn ($0.25 per bushel after September 1st); is currently staying at a hotel but is eagerly awaiting a position in a private home to teach for an hour or two a day; mentions that the whole state is crowded with lawyers; informs him that the land laws are complicated and provide most of the revenue to be gained in this profession; was obliged to ride with the driver when traveling to Cleburn as the stage was filled with ladies, and as a result was treated to the view of a "magnificent country"; describes the people as "healthy, but their eyes look dull, and they are generally listless and inanimate"; mentions that the people are hard-working and thrifty, and that Cleburn "makes no pretensions to anything like fashion or refinement, but they appear to be very good plain people."
    - Kate [?], Park Avenue, to "cousin" [?], n.p., 25 Jan[uary] 1875., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Took the hair that was sent immediately to Madame De Vourges to be made up as soon as it was received; informs her that Mary Garret's [sic] hair is so tangled that it would not be worth making it up, and the same is true for Mrs. Vest's; misses Comfort a great deal, but knows she will be happier being with her father; fears Comfort is sick; shares news of the family.
    - James H. Smith, Boston, Mass., to Dr. Rob[er]t [M.] Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 20 Feb[ruary] 1876., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Writes because he would like to know the date of his birth; asks also for the age of his sister Lucy, who is going to school at the Normal collage [sic]; would like to go to Williamsburg next fall before going to school.
    - R.B. Winder, Balt[imore, Maryland], to cousin Lauretta [Savage?], n.p., 13 Sept[ember] 1876., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Informs her that the package was sent back to Baltimore, but that he has sent it down again to Dr. Van Garrett, and it should be in Yorktown on Thursday morning; is sorry to hear of Cousin Sue's illness; sends his love to all.
    - Two letters written on the same page, 2 Oct[ober] 1877., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Julia Garrett, Nashville, [Tenn.], to "aunt" [?], n.p., 2 Oct[ober] 1877. Informs her that the children are greatly looking forward to the trip to going to see her; describes everyone as looking well; mentions the weather as being "real hot summer weather" and that no one is yet wearing winter hats or garments. 3 pp. ALS.
      Also contains the letter of: Willie Garrett, Nashville, [Tenn.], to "aunt" [?], n.p., n.d. Has spent one of his dimes on three apples but still has a quarter and a nickel left; mentions that he makes a nickel ever week for carrying the milk; informs her that the President passed through Nashville and they all had a flag to wave; is sent down each day to the meat store for Mama, but could not go today because his knee is sore. 2 pp. ALS.
    - Jno. [John ?], Eastville, Virginia, to sister Lauretta A. Savage, Williamsburg, Virginia, 14 Dec[ember 18]77., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Had built up his stock with dry goods and shoes, etc., and left town in October; still owes some money that has to be paid back; informs her that Mr. Bell has moved out to Hickory Ground, and that Clara Nottingham was married a week ago; would like to come to visit but would lose too much if he came now.
    - M.C. Watkins, Kenmore, to cousin Lottie Garrett, W[illia]msburg, Virginia, 28 May 1878., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Expresses grief for the death of Aunt Susan, her [LG] mother; asks why Susan was laid in the churchyard; sends her love to Uncle Robert; informs her that the sale of all her father's personal property at Chester will take place next Thursday.
    - E.G. Booth, Philadelphia, [Penn.], to Mrs. [Lauretta A.] Savage, n.p., 8 Nov[ember 18]78., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Informs her that the photograph she received is of a lady who claims to be 15, dating her existence from the date of her marriage; mentions that the lady would like to have a good husband to share her life with; has been advised to get married but to wait for a first rate chance.
    - Mary [?], Nashville, [Tennessee], to aunt Lauretta A. Savage, Williamsburg, Virginia, 26 Sept[ember], [1877-1881]., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Describes in great detail the visit of "our President" [Rutherford B. Hayes] to Nashville; mentions the appearance of Mrs. Hayes in terms of her dress and the manner in which she wears her hair; has been invited to Pulasky [sic]; sends love and asks for news.
  - Letters, 1890-1899., 9 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Josephine Nicholls, Mountain Lake, to cousin Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 20 Aug[ust] 1894., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Regrets not being able to visit Williamsburg this season; describes Mountain Lake as being "a lovely place and the people are as friendly and sociable as can be"; plans to stay in Mountain Lake a little while longer, then will go to a sulfur spring for a short time before returning to their home; has met a girl from Norfolk who had visited Williamsburg and knows both the Colemans and the Tylers; thanks Van through her for the college souvenir he sent her.
    - Cynthia B.J. Coleman, n.p., to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 20 Sept[ember] 1894., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Postmarked Williamsburg, Virginia Informs her that her father Dr. Coleman valued no man above her [LG] brother Van; is comforted by the friendship of them both; was disappointed that she did not come up to the house; realized later that she would need a special invitation [after her father's funeral].
    - Josephine H. Nicholls, White Sulphur Springs, [Virginia], to cousin Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 30 September 1894., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Is quite disappointed that they will not be able to meet this summer; hopes that she can travel to Petersburg next Saturday to be able to see her; has received several invitations to stay with various families, but the locations are too far off the way home that she will not be able to accept them; describes the nicest compliment she has received as coming from Virginia Lassiter, "who said I reminded her of you -- my voice and manner"; reports that Father has been ill with hay fever.
    - Frank W. Nicholls, Ridgefield, Thibodaux, La., to cousin Lottie Garrett, White Sulphur Springs, Eggleston, Virginia, 20 July 1895., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Has heard that she will be joining the party at Eggleston, along with Cousins Mary, Sue, and Van; regrets he cannot be there as well; reports that Cousin Sallie Winder had called her home Lorton; feels indebted to Cousin Mary's genealogical work and asks if there is any news related to her search; thanks her for the pictures of Lorton Hall and Lorton Church, which are now on display in the library at Ridgefield; reports that Carrie's health is almost entirely recovered; had read in a paper that a northern university had bestowed the degree of L.L.D. upon President Tyler of William and Mary; hopes that she will be able to visit his home soon.
    - Carra [?], n.p., to cousin Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 31 January 1896., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Informs her that Hattie is quite sick, and feels that she would feel better if she heard from Van; reports that Van has been silent for a long while, and so they believe he is very sick; mentions that "la grippe" is going around, and that Virginia is fighting it off while Hattie seems to be about to come down with a severe case of it; had thought the wedding was not till June, but was told by Hattie that she and Van have decided on the first of April; asks if she will be able to make a visit after the wedding.
    - Josephine H. Nicholls, n.p., to cousin Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 4 Feb[ruary] 1896., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Postmarked New Orleans, La. Has been quite busy as Mother and Hattie have been otherwise occupied, so all the social duties have fallen to her; has been fighting off the grippe; informs her that Miss Coleman of Williamsburg will be visiting Mrs. Burns in New Orleans; reports that Hattie is better but still looks tired from la grippe; mentions that there will be a masque ball held tonight but since there will be eight held before the Carnival closes, she does not feel obligated to go; hopes she feels better now.
    - Carra [?], n.p., to cousin Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 21 Feb[ruary] 1896., 12 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Postmarked New Orleans, La. Regrets that she cannot be in New Orleans with them for Mardi Gras; describes in very great detail the events of Mardi Gras; explains that the procession has just passed her house and will return from uptown soon; reports that she is writing a condolence letter for a friend whose husband has passed away, and is struck by the contrast of a man lying on his deathbed and the jollity and gaiety of the festival; informs her that Hattie will be married sometime after the 26th of April.
    - Julia Smith, Phoebus, Virginia, to Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 15 Nov[ember 18]96., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Is glad that the plates were received unbroken; hopes that the flowers she sent will live; expresses how highly she thinks of her by the simple act of sending her the platters; asks that she display the picture of Mr. Davis in her house; would like a picture of the prison and asks if her brother Robbie could send her one.
    - Mary Johnston, n.p., to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia 16 July 1897. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Postmarked Devon, [England]. Asks her to imagine her in this Devonshire town; describes her surroundings and her activities there; asks her to remember her.
  - Letters, 1900-1909., 19 items. (Box-folder 1:12-13)
    - Mary Johnston, Virginia Beach, Virginia, to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 19 March 1901., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Reassures her that she may have her photograph; will send her photograph as soon as she returns home; is pleased to be asked to become an annual member of the Colonial Capital branch of the A.P.V.A.; informs her that she and her cousin plan to be in Williamsburg for a few days; hopes to see her and her sister.
    - Mary Johnston, Birmingham, Ala., to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 12 April 1901., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Encloses the photograph that she had wanted; reports that she had been called home to Richmond suddenly because of the death of her sister.
    - Coralie H. Johnston, n.p., to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 13 April 1901., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Postmarked Richmond, Virginia Returns her book by mail; thanks her for the hours they spent together while she and Mary were in Williamsburg.
    - Mary Johnston, Warm Springs, Bath County, Virginia, to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 25 June 1902., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Would like to be with her in Williamsburgh [sic], "finals or no finals"; will not be able to visit because she is recovering from severe illnesses she has suffered all winter; remembers fondly the time she spent with her; hopes she has "a beautiful commencement week!"
    - Mary Johnston, Richmond, [Virginia], to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 2 April 1903., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:12)